Finding Aid for Affirmative Action Office (University of Michigan) records 1969-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Affirmative Action Office
  - General Files
    - 1971-1987
      - Appendices to the Affirmative Action Program, July 1973 (Box 20)
      - Department of Labor
        - Compliance Reviews
          - 1980, 6 folders (Box 20)
          - 1980-1985, 9 folders (Box 21)
      - Handicap
        - Accessibility
          - Counseling Center Building, 1982 (Box 21)
          - Handbook, 1983-1984 (Box 21)
        - Accommodations
          - Employee, 1973-1979 (Box 21)
          - School/College Reports, 1982 (Box 21)
        - Awareness Week, 1979 (Box 21)
        - Breakthrough (student group), 1982-1983 (Box 21)
        - Breakthrough News (newsletter), September 1981-March 1983 (Box 21)
        - Building Priorities Committee, 1978 (Box 21)
        - Crime Prevention, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
        - Dramatically Able Workshop, 1983 (Box 21)
        - Employment, 1975-1984 (Box 21)
        - Employment/Vocational Rehabilitation, 1976-1980 (Box 21)
        - IYDP (International Year of Disabled Persons)
          - Design that Enables, 1981 (Box 21)
          - Final Report, [1981-1982] (Box 21)
          - General, University, 1980-1982 (Box 21)
          - Mayor's Commission, 1978-1982 (Box 21)
          - Mayor's Commission--Education Subcommittee, 1981-1983 (Box 21)
          - Mayor's Commission--Minutes/Agendas, 1981-1982 (Box 21)
          - Nomination Committee, 1981 (Box 21)
          - Task Forces
            - Arts and Recreation, 1981-1982 (Box 21)
            - Education, 1981-1982 (Box 21)
            - General, 1981-1982 (Box 21)
            - Public Awareness, 1981-1982 (Box 21)
            - Rehabilitation, 1981-1982 (Box 21)
            - Steering Committee, 1982 (Box 21)
            - Transportation, 1979-1982; 2 folders (Box 21)
        - Jericho (handicap game), 1981-1982 (Box 22)
        - Report on Students, 1984 (Box 22)
        - Rowing
          - Correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box 22)
          - Equipment, 1982 (Box 22)
          - Funding, 1983-1984 (Box 22)
          - General, 1982-1985; 3 folders (Box 22)
          - Grant Proposal, 1984 (Box 22)
          - Support Letters, 1983-1984 (Box 22)
        - Student Achievement Award, 1981-1982 (Box 22)
      - Hispanics
        - General, 1982-1983 (Box 22)
        - Student/Faculty Awards, 1983-1985; 3 folders (Box 22)
      - Minorities
        - Black Women's History Project, 1984 (Box 22)
        - Bursley Show (Minority Pre-freshperson Orientation), 1983-1984 (Box 22)
        - Minority Males Steering Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 22)
        - Minority Students, Graduate, 1984 (Box 22)
        - Minority Women's Career Conference
          - 1979-1982, 2 folders (Box 22)
          - 1983-1985, 3 folders (Box 23)
        - Minority Women's Task Force, 1983-1985 (Box 23)
        - Office of Minority Student Services, 1980-1983 (Box 23)
        - Targeted Recruitment Program, 1984 (Box 23)
        - Women of Color Task Force--Planning Retreat, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Policy Statement-Female Radiation Workers, 1974 (Box 23)
      - Reports
        - Education Task Force of the Council for Disability Concerns--"Learning Disabilities", February 1987 (Box 23)
        - Task Force on Minority Concerns, April 1979 (Box 23)
      - Retreat--Goals and Projects, 1980-1981 (Box 23)
      - Sexual Harassment
        - "Combating Sexual Harassment: Establishing a Program", May 1982 (Box 23)
        - General, 1979-1983; 5 folders (Box 23)
      - Sexual Orientation
        - General, 1981-1985; 3 folders (Box 23)
        - Law School Inquiry re: Recruiters, 1983 (Box 23)
        - Subcommittee on Student Relations, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Staff Meetings (mostly administrative concerns), 1981-1984
        - 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Tenure
        - Faculty Tenure Workshop/Evaluations, 1981-1984; 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Women
        - Barbour Summer Program, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
        - Graduate Women's Network, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
        - International Women's Decade
          - Arvonne Fraser, 1986 (Box 24)
          - Budget, 1984-1985 (Box 24)
        - International Year Celebration Coordinating Committee, 1983-1984; 3 folders (Box 24)
        - Women's Career Fair, 1981-1984; 2 folders (Box 24)
        - Women's Network
          - Budget Reviews, 1983 (Box 24)
          - Correspondence Reports, 1980-1984 (Box 24)
          - Minutes, 1980-1984 (Box 24)
        - Women's Studies Program
          - Great Lakes Colleges Association, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
          - Minutes, 1980-1984 (Box 24)
    - 1975-1987
      The General Files covering the years 1975-1987 (1 linear foot) include correspondence with government agencies and information on proposed changes in federal government affirmative action reporting practices. There are, in addition, copies of presentations given by the director of the Affirmative Action Office to university and community groups. This subgroup is arranged alphabetically by topic.
      - Correspondence, HEW-OCR Title IX
        - 1976-1977 (Box 26)
        - 1978-1979 (Box 26)
        - 1980, 3 folders (Box 26)
      - Data Responses, 1980 (Box 26)
      - Outside Regulatory Agencies, Proposed Revisions
        - 1975 (Box 26)
        - 1976 (Box 26)
      - Presentations (by director to the university community)
        - 1981-1982 (Box 26)
        - 1982-1983 (Box 26)
        - 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 26)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 26)
        - 1985-1986 (Box 26)
        - 1987 (Box 26)
      - Standard Practice Guide revisions, 1980-1982 (Box 26)
      - Women
        - Minority Women's Taskforce, 1983-1985 (Box 26)
        - Speech Materials for Vivian Shapiro/Sarah Power (Box 26)
    - 1972-1993
      The General Files, 1972-1993 are arranged in alphabetical order and include the records of various task forces and the documentation of minority issues on campus. The Michigan Employment Relations Commission files document the unsuccessful attempt of the University of Michigan Flint faculty to become unionized.
      - Accessibility Task Force, 1987-1990 (Box 37)
      - Affirmative Action Coordinators
        - Minutes/Agendas
          - 1985/86 (Box 37)
          - 1986/87 (Box 37)
          - 1987-1990 (Box 37)
        - Notebook, 1980-1982; 2 folders (Box 37)
      - AIDS Task Force, 1988-1990 (Box 37)
      - Career Ladders, 1972-1986 (Box 37)
      - Compliance
        - Employment Statistics, 1967-1967 (Box 37)
        - Job Groups, 1980-1984 (Box 37)
      - Council for Disability Concerns, 1981-1990 (Box 37)
      - Discrimination
        - Discrimination and Discriminatory Harassment Policies, 1988 (Box 37)
        - Discrimination and Discriminatory Harassment by Faculty and Staff, Policies on, 1989 (Box 37)
      - Education Task Force, 1985-1989 (Box 37)
      - Employment Task Force (minutes), 1988-1990 (Box 37)
      - Enrollment (non-resident aliens), 1983-1986 (Box 37)
      - Executive Committee Composition, 1983 (Box 37)
      - Faculty
        - Incentive Proposal, 1983 (Box 37)
        - Statistics, 1980-1985 (Box 37)
      - Freedom on the River (recreational rowing program for people with mobility impairments), 1985-1990 (Box 37)
      - Grievance Procedures (staff), 1973-1979 (Box 37)
      - Handicap (504 transition plan), 1978-1979 (Box 37)
      - Internships, 1979-1980 (Box 37)
      - Indian Affairs, Michigan Commission on, 1981 (Box 37)
      - King/Parks Fellowship Program, 1986/87 (Box 37)
      - Michigan Association of Affirmative Action Officials, 1982-1985 (Box 38)
      - Michigan Employment Relations Commission (MERC)
        - Background Materials, 1992-1993; 4 folders (Box 38)
          v
        - Decision, 1993 (Box 38)
      - Minorities
        - Advisory Committee for Undergraduate Minority Recruitment, 1985-1987 (Box 38)
        - Black Action Movement (BAM) (historical), 1987 (Box 38)
        - Black Leadership Advisory Council, 1984-1987 (Box 38)
        - Council for Minority Concerns, 1981-1986 (Box 38)
        - Hispanic Student Concerns, 1973-1974 (Box 38)
        - Enrollment/Recruitment, 1985-1987 (Box 38)
        - Minority Proposals, 1982-1985 (Box 38)
        - Status of Black Faculty Members at the University of Michigan Ann Arbor Campus (report), 1980 (Box 38)
      - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1983-1986 (Box 38)
      - Program Changes, 1983-1984 (Box 38)
      - Task Force on Sexual Orientation, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 38)
      - University Age Concerns Council, 1985-1990 (Box 38)
      - University Housing, 1972-1984 (Box 38)
      - Women
        - Academic Women's Caucus (re: female faculty), 1974-1984 (Box 38)
        - Public Forum, "The Future of Women at the University of Michigan", 1988 (Box 38)
        - Women's Initiative Group (WING), 1990, 2 folders (Box 38)
  - Affirmative Action Coordinators
    The Affirmative Action Coordinators series (.5 linear feet) is records of an independent advisory group consisting of Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint representatives from each school and/or college of the university, and each vice-presidential area. The series is comprised of six folders of agendas and minutes. Topics covered in the group's minutes include university policy regarding sexual harassment, administrative appointments, hiring procedures, and reports from the Affirmative Action Office.
    - Agenda/Minutes, 1980-1985; 6 folders (Box 20)
  - Audio-Visual Materials
    The Audio-Visual Materials series includes audio-cassettes, photographs, videocassettes and videotapes. Most come from the university's observance of International Women's Year in 1976. Included are discussions about the development and evolution of affirmative action programs and a speech and press conference given by Betty Friedan. There is also a small group of 30 black and white prints and 7 proof sheets depicting handicap accessibility devices and handicapped persons participating in rowing programs.
    - Audio-Cassettes
      - Dr. Freddie Lang Grooms (sp?) of Florida State University re Effects of Executive Order 11246 (Box 12)
    - Photographs
      - Commission for Women "Career Placement Packet" (Box 12)
      - Commission on Women "Community Helpers and Professional Women's Report" (Box 12)
      - Women's Information Network Bulletin (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous (na 9043) (Box 12)
      - Accessibility (undated) (Box 12)
      - Rowing Program, 1982 (Box 12)
    - Videocassettes
      - Betty Friedan, Speech during International Women's Year observance at University of Michigan, 2 videotapes (Box 12)
      - Betty Friedan, Press Conference, International Women's Year observance at University of Michigan (Box 12)
    - Videotapes
      - Evaluation of Affirmative Action (Box 12)
  - Reports
    The Reports series (10 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically by topic. The largest set of reports is compliance reports (1980-1988), prepared pursuant to federal regulations. The reports are arranged by University of Michigan campus (Ann Arbor, Dearborn, Flint), with a separate run for the University Hospital. Missing volumes are noted on the contents list. The compliance reports provide extensive data on the composition of the university work force. Summaries of the compliance reports are also available in the Publications subgroup (Report to the Regents).
    In preparing the compliance reports the Affirmative Action Office relies in part on utilization analyses and workforce analyses. Utilization analyses result in computer generated reports of the university workforce that compare the current workforce with a "model staff" of women and/or minorities. Reports are available for the years 1977-1979 and provide useful, detailed analysis of women and/or minorities in the university workforce. Workforce analyses are available from 1977 to 1980 and are listings of regular university job titles by job groups. The total number of employees in each job is reported, as well as the total number of females and the total number of minorities. For a more complete explanation of terms used in Affirmative Action reports, the researcher should examine the Reports to the Regents, located in the Publications subgroup.
    The Monthly Status Reports, covering the years 1979-1987, detail the preparation of the federal compliance reports and also the various support and community involvement activities of the Affirmation Action Office. Each staff member submits a monthly report on his or her activities. The Monthly Status Reports are useful for gaining an overview of the daily work of the Affirmative Action Office.
    - Availability Assessment, 1978-1979; 1 volumes (Box 27)
    - Compliance Program Reports
      - Ann Arbor Campus
        - 1979-1980, 1 volumes (Box 27)
        - 1980-1981, 1 volumes (Box 27)
          (Missing volumes II-VIII)
        - 1981-1982, 3 volumes (Box 27)
          (Missing volumes I-III)
        - 1983-1984, 2 volumes (Box 27)
          (Missing volumes II and III)
        - 1984-1985, 6 volumes (Box 27)
          (Missing volumes I and II)
        - 1984-1985, 4 volumes (Box 28)
          (Missing volume I)
        - 1986-1987, 1 volumes (Box 28)
          (Missing volumes I-III and VI-VIII)
      - Dearborn Campus
        - 1980-1981, 2 volumes (Box 28)
        - 1981-1982, 3 volumes (Box 28)
        - 1982-1983, 2 volumes (Box 28)
          (Missing volumes II and III; VIII)
        - 1983-1984, 1 volumes (Box 28)
        - 1984-1985, 2 volumes (Box 28)
        - 1985-1986, 1 volumes (Box 28)
        - 1987-1988, 1 volumes (Box 28)
      - Flint Campus
        - 1980-1981, 2 volumes (Box 29)
        - 1981-1982, 2 volumes (Box 29)
        - 1982-1983, 2 volumes (Box 29)
        - 1983-1984, 1 volumes (Box 29)
        - 1984-1985, 3 volumes (Box 29)
        - 1985-1986, 1 volumes (Box 29)
      - University Hospitals
        - 1980-1981, 2 volumes (Box 29)
          (Missing volumes II and VI-VIII)
        - 1981-1982, 3 volumes (Box 29)
          (Missing volumes VI-VIII)
        - 1982-1983, 2 volumes (Box 29)
        - 1983-1984, 1 volumes (Box 29)
          (Missing volumes I and VI-VIII)
        - 1985-1986, 1 volumes (Box 29)
          (Missing volumes III, V, and VIII)
    - Faculty Availability, 1978; 1 volumes (Box 30)
    - Goal Evaluations
      - 1977-1978, 1 volumes (Box 30)
      - 1978-1980, 1 volumes (Box 30)
    - HEW-OCR Compliance Review, 1976-1977; 3 volumes (Box 30)
    - Monthly Status Reports
      - 1979 (Box 30)
      - 1980 (Box 30)
      - 1981 (Box 30)
      - 1982 (Box 31)
      - 1983 (Box 31)
      - January-June 1984 (Box 31)
      - July 1984-June 1985 (Box 31)
      - July 1985-June 1986 (Box 31)
      - July 1986-June 1987 (Box 31)
    - People and Issues in Equal Opportunity, 1981 (Box 31)
    - Summaries of Employment and Affirmative Action Data by EEO6 Occupational Groups, 1980-1981 (Box 31)
    - Utilization Analysis
      - 1977-1978, 6 volumes (Box 31)
      - 1977-1978, 2 volumes (Box 32)
      - 1978-1979, 8 volumes (Box 32)
      - 1979-1980, 6 volumes (Box 33)
    - Workforce Analysis
      - 10/07/1977, 2 volumes (Box 33)
      - 10/07/1977, 3 volumes (Box 34)
      - 1977-1978, 3 volumes (Box 34)
      - 1978-1979, 6 volumes (Box 35)
      - 1979-1980, 4 volumes (Box 36)
  - Title IX Files
    The Title IX Files are primarily 1976 Self-Evaluation reports that were required of all units on campus
    - Compliance (University of Michigan Dearborn), 1976 (Box 39)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 39)
    - Employment Questionnaire, undated (Box 39)
    - Self Evaluation, 1976
      - General (Box 39)
      - Academic Affairs (Box 39)
      - Architecture and Urban Planning, College of (Box 39)
      - Art, School of (Box 39)
      - Athletic Department (Box 39)
      - Business Administration, School of (Box 39)
      - Dental School, 1973-1976 (Box 39)
      - Education, School of (Box 39)
      - Engineering, College of (Box 39)
      - Horace Rackham School of Graduate Studies (Box 39)
      - Housing Division (Box 39)
      - Law School (Box 39)
      - Library Science, School of (Box 39)
      - Literature, Science and the Arts, College of (Box 39)
      - Medical School (Box 39)
      - Music, School of (Box 39)
      - Natural Resources, School of (Box 39)
      - Nursing, School of (Box 39)
      - Pharmacy, College of (Box 39)
      - Presidential Units (Box 39)
      - Public Health, School of (Box 39)
      - Research Units (Box 39)
      - Social Work, School of (Box 39)
      - Student Services, 1976-1978 (Box 39)
      - University of Michigan Dearborn, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 39)
      - University of Michigan Flint, 1976 (Box 39)
- Commission for Minority Affairs
  The first folder in the Commission for Minority Affairs subgroup, Bylaws, will give the researcher information about the purpose and structure of the commission. Other files contain routine correspondence, memoranda and notices, minutes, and several issues of the commission newsletter. Major areas of interest to the commission were minority student recruitment and a survey of minority students in graduate programs at the university.
  - Topical files
    - Bylaws (Box 3)
    - Black Faculty and Staff Association, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Black Organizations on Campus (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
    - Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills-Puerto Rican Studies, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Coalition of Student Associations, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Committees
      - Asian American Affairs, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
      - Minority Women, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Women and Minority Student Services, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda and Notices, 1973-1978 (Box 3)
    - Minority Student Recruitment, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Minutes, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Newsletter, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Report of the Committee to Study Advocacy at the University of Michigan, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Survey of Minority Students in Graduate Programs at the University of Michigan, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Task Force on Minority Concerns, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - Third World Ethnic Film Festival, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
- Commission for Women
  Records of the Commission contain papers relating to the history, operating procedures, and organization and structure of the commission as well as topical information, correspondence, committees, cluster, and school and department files. Much of the work of the commission was done through committees. Clusters were based on units within the university and were set up to review affirmative action goals. Cluster and committee files contain minutes, memoranda, reports, and recommendations. Correspondence files are arranged chronologically and include the correspondence of chairwomen Barbara Newell, Virginia Davis Nordin, and Eunice Burns, and co-chairwoman Sarah Goddard Power. Papers in the topical files contain correspondence and memoranda, recommendations, and background material. There is an overlap of information and papers among the topical, committee, and general correspondence files. Schools and Departments files consist mainly of correspondence relating to charges of discrimination or unfair treatment.
  Commissions for Women were established within the Medical Center, Schools of Education and Public Health, and on the Dearborn campus. Each of these commissions had a liaison reporting to the president's commission. Included in the files of the Commission for Women are papers relating to these commissions and the Commission for Minority Groups.
  The subgroup contains a single audio cassette of an International Women's Year banquet held on April 9, 1976. Addie Wyatt, a leader in the battle against sexual and racial discrimination, was the speaker. She was introduced by Sarah Goddard Power, and a resolution honoring her was read by Representative Perry Bullard.
  The CFW records include a complete run of the "Women's Information Network Bulletin" for the years 1972 to 1985. The "Women's Information Network Bulletins", published by the commission, document its continuing emphasis on campus child care, disability benefits, and sexual harassment.
  - Administrative Files
    - History (Box 3)
    - Operating Procedures, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Organization and Structure (Box 3)
    - Academic Administration Internship, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    - Advocate Training Program, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Affirmative Action Program
      - 1971 (Box 3)
      - 1972 (Box 3)
      - 1973-1977 (Box 3)
    - Appointment Process, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - Assertiveness Training, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Assessment Center, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Athletics/Athletic Facilities, 1972-1976 (Box 4)
    - Barbour-Waterman Gymnasiums, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - Battered Women (Workshop), 1977 (Box 4)
    - Cancer Information Day, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Child Care
      - General File, 1970-1980 (Box 4)
      - Pound House Children's Center, 1973-1978 (Box 4)
    - Clusters
      - Cluster Briefs (Newsletter), 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Cluster 1 (Student Services, University Relations, Rackham, Administration, Business and Finance), 1971 (Box 4)
      - Cluster 7 (Social Work, Intercollegiate Athletics, Education, Music), 1969-1971 (Box 4)
      - Cluster 8 (Libraries, Museums, School of Library Science), 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      - Cluster Communications Committee (originally called Cluster Coordinating Committee), 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Papers, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Review of Affirmative Action Goals, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Commissions
      - Minority Groups, 1971-1975 (Box 4)
      - Women
        - Dearborn, 1971-1977 (Box 4)
        - Medical Center
          - 1972-1974 (Box 4)
          - 1975-1976 (Box 4)
        - School of Education, 1971-1974 (Box 4)
        - School of Public Health, 1971-1974 (Box 4)
    - Committees
      - Budget, 1971; 1973 (Box 4)
      - Clerical, 1972; 1974 (Box 4)
      - Complaint Appeal, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
      - Economic Status of the Faculty, 1972-1974 (Box 4)
      - Education
        - 1971, 1973 (Box 4)
        - Media Group Subcommittee, 1971; 1975 (Box 4)
      - Federal Guidelines, 1972 (Box 4)
      - File Review
        - 1971 (Box 4)
        - 1972 (Box 4)
        - 1973 (Box 4)
        - 1974 (Box 4)
      - Fringe Benefits, 1971-1974 (Box 4)
      - Grievance
        - Academic, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
        - Non-Academic, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      - Job Posting, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
      - Long Range Planning, 1973-1975 (Box 5)
      - Nominating
        - 1971-1976 (Box 5)
        - 1977-1981 (Box 5)
      - Percentage Increase, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      - Personnel Policies
        - 1973 (Box 5)
        - 1974-1977 (Box 5)
      - Professional and Administrative Women, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      - Program, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
      - Research, 1971-1973 (Box 5)
      - Returning Student, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
      - Search, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
      - Security (personal safety), 1974-1977 (Box 5)
      - Sex-Biased Language, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - Student, 1971-1974 (Box 5)
      - Women's Health Services, 1971-1973 (Box 5)
    - Department of Labor Revised Order No. 4, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Equal Pay, 1971-1973 (Box 5)
    - Equal Rights Amendment, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Reform Coalition, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - File Review
      - General File, 1971-1975 (Box 5)
      - Women's Commission Representative, 1971-1973 (Box 5)
    - Fleming Follow, 1971-1972; 1974 (Box 5)
    - Fringe Benefits, 1973-1974; 1977 (Box 5)
    - General Correspondence
      - 1970-1971 (Box 5)
      - 1972
        - January-February (Box 5)
        - March-April (Box 5)
        - May-June (Box 5)
        - July-August (Box 5)
        - September-December (Box 5)
      - 1973 (Box 5)
      - 1974 (Box 5)
      - 1975 (Box 6)